Hello, and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today we're
going to be learning about how to
calculate theoretical n percent yield.
Now, when is this really important?
Well, typically it has to do with
stoichiometry and relating to your work
that you do within the laboratory setting.
Percent yield is equal to the actual
yield, which is how much you obtain
within an experiment, so it's also
commonly called the experimental yield,
divided by the theoretical yield.
which is how much you obtain when
you calculate it using stoichiometry.
So just using your calculators and going
through all the mathematical steps of
what you've been learning about in general
chemistry, and we times it by 100%.
Now, why is it that we
try to calculate this?
Let's take a look at it.
Now, throughout stoichiometry, we
make the assumption that all reactants
100 percent convert to products.
meaning that we are assuming
that we are perfect.
The thing is, as we all
know, we are not perfect.
We make errors in the lab.
It is not possible to get
100 percent in chemistry.
You always are making errors all
over the place, which is normal.
You make errors because you're learning.
You're trying to get
your lab skills better.
Sometimes reactions don't completely
occur the way you want them to.
But there are errors and these are
things that we have to deal with.
Now, where can these errors come up from?
Well, sometimes they can come
from maybe just transferring
chemicals between glassware.
It's really easy to see like, Hey,
some, some solid got left here.
Maybe when you're mixing, you
see it on the stirring rod or on
the spatulas or on the beakers.
Uh, it's very common the reaction
doesn't go to completion or maybe
you didn't wait long enough.
Like, okay, the lab manual said 15
minutes, but hey, your lab partner
wanted to leave a little early.
So you just did it for five minutes.
So maybe there was an error.
Other things that could be made
is maybe you made a side product,
meaning that another reaction
occurred without your knowledge.
Or the reactant isn't P or let's say the
reactants weren't even pure to begin with.
So let's say if you just had like some,
maybe not the best quality ingredients.
Well, then, yeah, you're going
to have different, different, uh,
read it products in the very end
or just human error to begin with.
Maybe you just made a mistake or
forgot to do something or added
too much water or whatever it
is, there are going to be errors.
So when we are calculating this.
We calculate on paper the theoretical
yield, which is something that
you've been doing all along.
This is all stoichiometry calculations.
So whether it's mass to mass, gas
stoichiometry, solution stoichiometry,
you're assuming that you have
a perfect experiment, right?
This is all about mass
conservation and being Perfect.
And that is a true law.
However, we do make errors and
there is mass that can be lost.
So if something is lost, this
is what the actual yield is
and what we measure in lab.
So we compare the two numbers
to see, well, how good did you
do when you were in the lab?
It gives us a reference point
to see, can we improve, right?
One of the things about school is all
about improvement and getting better.
better, right?
If you were getting 100 percent on
everything going throughout the gate, then
you don't need to be in school, right?
You can just start working in
the field that you want to be in.
But we do this because we want to learn.
We want to grow.
And the whole idea here is when it comes
to chemistry is products are always lost.
We're always trying to search for them
with our little magnifying glass, but
we always are losing a little bit.
So we're going to be using this formula
to help us try to understand this.
So let's try to take a look at an example
of how this could work and then we'll get
into some harder stoichiometry examples.
In the reaction box, there are 6 moles of
hydrogen gas and 3 moles of nitrogen gas.
Based on the reaction, determine
the theoretical yield based on
the following chemical expression.
Well, if we were doing this and we
wanted to figure out exactly how
much ammonia you were going to make,
which is your theoretical yield.
What would we do?
Well, the first thing is that we
saw is that we had 6 moles of H2.
So if we wanted to convert that using
this formula, well, we would just use
our molar coefficients, and we can see
that, okay, for every 3 We are going
to be making two moles of ammonia.
So if we were to do this little
conversion here, we are going to
quickly see that we would obtain four
moles of ammonia that are possible.
Now, the thing is that this is a
limiting reagent problem because you
were given two different starting points.
We were also told, hey, we have
three moles of nitrogen in that
box, too, and we can see it as well.
There are these little, the little,
uh, blue orbs that are here.
Um, are reacting as well.
So if I have three moles of nitrogen
and from our chemical equation, we can
see that one mole of nitrogen reacts
and it creates two moles of ammonia.
Well, this is going to make a
total of six moles of ammonia.
Well, which one is the theoretical yield?
Well, it's all about which
made less out of the two.
So our answer in this case is going to be
that hydrogen was the limiting reagent.
And our possible theoretical
yield is going to be, uh, going
to be hydrogen in this case
making only four moles of ammonia.
Okay?
So our theoretical yield is four.
Now, if we wanted to calculate,
let's say, percent yield, how
exactly would you do this?
Well, so let's say if, however, you
actually only created 3 moles of ammonia
in the lab, what is your percent yield?
Well, so this is your actual,
which is 3, your theoretical was 4.
So what do you got to do is you'll take
3 moles, which is your actual yield.
Divide that by 4 moles,
which was our theoretical.
We calculated that together.
So telling us that you have about a 75
percent yield within your reaction, which
is pretty good actually in chemistry
to get about a 75 percent yield.
A lot of times when you're doing organic
chemistry, you might be lucky if you
even get 5 or 10 percent yield depending
on what reaction you were trying to do.
So that's the basic idea.
How much were you supposed to
make and how much did you actually
make when you did the experiment?
All right.
Let's take a look at some
different stoichiometry examples.
from the air to form lithium bicarbonate.
So lithium hydroxide plus CO2
makes lithium bicarbonate or
lithium hydrogen carbonate.
Uh, what is the percent yield of lithium
bicarbonate for the reaction if 50
grams of lithium hydroxide gives 72.
8 grams of lithium bicarbonate?
The first thing is that what a lot of
students will do is they want to just
divide these two numbers and then times
it by 100 percent and think they are done.
The thing is that would
be very, very wrong.
We can't just take 50
grams and divide it by 72.
8 and be done with the problem.
We need to convert it to be
the same molecule when we are
comparing the two numbers.
So we need to do the stoichiometry
for 50 grams of lithium hydroxide.
and then convert it to
lithium bicarbonate.
So in this case, using mass
stoichiometry to do the conversion.
So now whenever we do these, we
always need to check if, if the
chemical equation is balanced.
Typically the easiest way to know if it
is, is if you see coefficients, but with
this one, there are no coefficients,
but you can, you might be able to
quickly identify that it is balanced.
You have one lithium on each side,
one carbon, and then three oxygens.
So it's pretty quick to see that,
that this one is balanced, so we
don't have to do anything else.
So, what we are going to do is we need
to calculate what the theoretical yield
is using stoichiometry conversions.
So we want to write down all the
important pieces of information that
we were given, which was 50 grams
of lithium hydroxide, and then what
our actual yield was, which was 72.
8.
Keep in mind, whenever there's
actual yields involved, It's always
generally given to you in some form
or it's what you did in the lab.
It has to either be given to
you or you did it yourself.
There's no, you generally
can't calculate it unless you
were given the percent yield.
Um, you have to, usually
something has to be given to you.
So if we were to do this, we have 50
grams of lithium hydroxide, so LiOH
at our disposal, and we are going to
convert this to lithium bicarbonate.
So what is our first step to do that?
Well, whenever we are given a
mass, our goal is always the mole.
So we need to use the molar mass
of lithium hydroxide to get there.
So what we'll do is we'll use our
periodic table and you'll get 23.
938 grams A lithium hydroxide,
and if you're watching this, I
recommend you check that so you can
practice it, and that's equivalent
to one mole of lithium hydroxide.
Now from there, what we're going to
do is use our chemical equation, which
we can see it's a one to one ratio,
so one mole of LiOH is equivalent
to one mole of LiHCO3, alright?
So that's a one to one ratio.
And let's change the hydroxide
to match the formula too.
Now from there, we're now going
to use the molar mass of lithium
hydroxide to cancel out the last part.
But before we do that, let's just
show our units are all canceling,
so grams cancelled grams, and
then moles cancelled moles.
Alright, so our molar mass of
lithium hydroxide is going to
be one mole is equivalent to 67.
956 grams.
And we can see that, hey, these canceled
as well, so one mole cancels one mole.
And what we will get in the end is 141.
94 grams of LiHCO3.
So this is your theoretical yield that
we are here and we have labeled in pink.
What do we got to do now?
How do we figure out the percent yield?
Well, the whole entire thing with
the percent yield is we got to kind
of plug it into the formula below.
So we were given 72.
8 grams is how much we started with.
So what we are going to do is
essentially take that value and
then divide it by our 141 0.
94 grams and we're going to times that
by 100 percent and what we are going to
end up having in the end is about 51.
3 percent is our yield in this problem.
So which isn't, which is pretty good.
I know it sounds like a really low number,
but in terms of percent yields, this is
pretty good for most chemical reactions.
You always want to get higher, but
it's not bad for a chemical reaction.
Let's look at another example.
So we want to find the
actual yield in this problem.
So we're going to be working
backwards, meaning that aluminum
reacts with oxygen to produce aluminum
oxide via the following reaction.
So we have four aluminum reacting with
three oxygen to make two aluminum oxide.
So what we are going to do is we're
going to calculate the mass of
aluminum that can be produced if the
reaction of 50 grams of aluminum with
excess oxygen has a yield of 75%.
First things first is we need to
calculate the theoretical yield
starting with 50 grams of aluminum.
So we're going to convert that to
aluminum oxide in this problem.
So we've got to kind of look through what
all the important piece of information is.
So, right, there's a lot of words here.
But we only need a few of these more
important terms, which was essentially we
have 50 grams of aluminum, excess oxygen
means it's not going to run out, and then
we have 75 percent is what our yield is.
So we're starting with 50.
So what we're going to do is calculate
what that theoretical yield is.
Um, so we're going to start
with 50 grams of aluminum and
we need to get that to moles.
So how do we get a mass to moles?
Well, we need to use the
molar mass to do that.
So we're going to use our periodic
table to see that, okay, 26.
98 grams of aluminum is equivalent
to one mole of aluminum.
Now we are interested in getting to the
final product, which is aluminum oxide.
So we need to use our molar
coefficients to get there.
So we see that four moles of
aluminum is equivalent to two moles.
Of AL 2 0 3, then we are going to
use the molar mass of aluminum oxide
to get two grams as our final step.
So one mole of AL 2 0 3 is equivalent
to 101.957 grams a L 2 0 3.
Before we continue, we want
to double check did all of
our units cancel properly?
So, we see grams are opposite each
other, they cancelled, moles cancelled
moles of aluminum, and then moles of
aluminum oxide cancelled moles of aluminum
oxide, leaving us only with the grams.
So when we solve this,
we'll take 50 divided by 26.
98 times by 2, Divide by
4, then multiply by 101.
97, and what we will get for a
theoretical yield is about 94.
5 grams of Al2O3.
This is our theoretical yield here,
which is what we've been doing all
along when it comes to stoichiometry.
It's nothing new, it's just we're
just labeling it a little differently.
Calculate the actual yield.
How do we do it?
Well, the thing is, we
were given that we had 75%.
percent yield in the problem.
So what we are going to do is we're going
to pretty much take the problem and plug
in the theoretical yield that we got.
So we have our actual yield and
then our theoretical was 94.
5 grams of Al2O3.
So the first thing we're going
to do is we're going to move the
100 percent to the other side.
And what we'll quickly get is, alright,
75 divided by 100, we'll get 0.
75, and that's gonna be equal to our
actual divided by our theoretical.
And then we will multiply
both sides by 94.
5, so that way we get
that number by itself.
And
then what we will have for
our actual yield is 70.
9 grams, that's how much
they actually got in lab.
So this is if you had to calculate actual
yield, but as I mentioned before, this has
to be a number that's somehow calculated.
given to you.
As you saw, it was given via
the percent yield this time.
Um, it's something that you
have to have to physically do.
All right.
So this has been my video on
percent yield and actual yield.
This is just another check for
yourself to see how you did when
you're comparing your lab data to
what you actually could theoretically
get if the reaction went Lawlessly.
All right.
So thank you so much for listening.
If you need help, please reach out, email
me, comment below, uh, ask me in class.
I hope that this does help you.
If not, then I'm sorry.
Um, but if this is your first time here,
please hit that like and subscribe button.
Please keep supporting the channel.
I really appreciate all of you and
I hope you have a wonderful day.
All right.
I will see you all later.
Bye now.